<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The case of Griffith Wynn an infant, son, and heir apparent of Tho. Wynn Esq., and of Thomas Bodvile an infant, and of the said Tho. Wynn the father. Humbly presented to the consideration of the honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses in Parliament assembled.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 22 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02582</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C916A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R173521</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">53981614</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 53981614</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180145</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02582)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180145)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2818:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The case of Griffith Wynn an infant, son, and heir apparent of Tho. Wynn Esq., and of Thomas Bodvile an infant, and of the said Tho. Wynn the father. Humbly presented to the consideration of the honourable the knights, citizens, and burgesses in Parliament assembled.</title>
                  <author>Wynn, Thomas, Esq.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bodvile, John, d. 1663 --  Will --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Wynn, Griffith.</term>
               <term>Wynn, Thomas, --  Esq.</term>
               <term>Inheritance and succession --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180145:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The CASE of <hi>GRIFFITH WYNN</hi> an Infant, Son and Heir apparent of <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> Eſq; and of <hi>Thomas Bodvile</hi> an Infant, and of the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> the Father.</head>
            <head type="sub">Humbly preſented to the conſideration of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable the Knights, Citizens, and Burgeſſes in Parliament aſſembled.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Humbly ſheweth,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THat <hi>John Bodvile</hi> of <hi>Bodvile</hi> in the County of <hi>Carnarvan</hi> Eſquire, being ſeized of ſeveral Mannors and Lands in the Counties of <hi>Carnarvan</hi> and <hi>Angleſey,</hi> of the value of 1800 <hi>l. per an.</hi> did in conſideration of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Anne,</hi> the Daughter of Sir <hi>William Ruſſell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">20 <hi>March,</hi> 1639.</note> ſettle a Joynture upon the ſaid <hi>Anne</hi> of 600 <hi>l. per an.</hi> and did ſettle all his ſaid Mannors and Lands, and the Reverſions of his Wife's Joynture upon himſelf, and the Heirs Males of his Body, begotten on the Body of the ſaid <hi>Anne,</hi> the Remainder to his own right Heirs with power if he had Iſſue Male and Female to charge the Eſtate with 500 <hi>l. per an.</hi> untill ſuch Daughters ſhall have received 1500 <hi>l.</hi> Portions; and if he had no Sons, but Daughters, then the Eſtate was charged with 5000 <hi>l.</hi> to ſuch Daughter or Daughters, to be equally devided amongſt them; <hi>John Bodvile</hi> had Iſſue by <hi>Anne;</hi> Daughters, <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> and no Iſſue Male; <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dyed in 1661 without Iſſue: great differences happened between the ſaid <hi>John Bodvile</hi> and <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife; and the ſaid <hi>John Bodvile</hi> having been a Collonel for the King, his Wife did procure Warrants for his apprehenſion, and endeavoured to have him tryed by a High Court of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> of which ſaid Warrants the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> the Father gave the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> notice; whereupon the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> fled into the Iſle of <hi>Man,</hi> and thence into <hi>Holland;</hi> and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> at his deſire, ſtayed in <hi>London</hi> 21 Months from his Wife and Children, and did correſpond with Mr. <hi>Bodvile;</hi> which, if diſcovered, had proved dangerous to Mr. <hi>Wynn:</hi> And in the year 1649. he gave Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> notice of a general Compoſition for <hi>North-Wales,</hi> which was then ſhortly to paſs, excepting ſuch as had been in Armes, and then beyond the Sea when it paſſed; whereupon the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> repaired to <hi>London,</hi> and the ſaid Act ſoon after paſſed, whereby his Life and Eſtate was preſerved; whereupon the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> by her power with <hi>Oliver,</hi> did get an Act of the then pretended Parliament for Allimony, and obtained a Decree in Chancery for 500 <hi>l. per an.</hi> to be paid her out of his Eſtate. And in the year 1650 upon her Petition, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s Eſtate was put into the Bill of Sale, notwithſtanding his Compoſition, and the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was to continue the enjoyment of her 500 <hi>l. per an.</hi> and ſhe obtained a Sequeſtration of Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s whole Eſtate for the payment of the ſaid 500 <hi>l. per an.</hi> by colour whereof the Lady <hi>Bodvile,</hi> Mother of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> in the year 1656. was turned out of the poſſeſſion of her Dowry, whereby ſhe was diſabled to relieve her Son; and Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was forced to take 1000 <hi>l.</hi> for 3555 <hi>l.</hi> 2 <hi>s</hi> 10 <hi>d.</hi> of his Wife's Portion unpaid, elſe he was threatned they would make a diſcovery of it to the Committee, and he ſhould loſe all. And the ſaid Mrs. <hi>Bodvile</hi> in the year 1657 did marry her Daughter <hi>Sarah</hi> to Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> without the conſent or knowledge of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> at which Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:180145:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:180145:3"/>was highly diſpleaſed. And in or about <hi>May</hi> 1662 Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was arreſted at the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of his Wife for her Allimony, upon a Commiſſion of Rebellion out of Chancery; which was made appear, was with the privity of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> who was preſent with his then Servants <hi>Lewes</hi> and <hi>Morris,</hi> and the Bayliffs who were then to arreſt him, to betray and diſcover the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> to the arreſt of the ſaid Bayliffs, who afterwards arreſted Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> about 11 of the clock at night, and immediately car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him away to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> where they kept him ſecret for ſeveral dayes and nights from all him Friends, and Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> had notice ſent him of the Arreſt early next morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. During which reſtraint <hi>Morris</hi> told Mr. <hi>Moſtin,</hi> were he Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> he would take Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> and pinne him in a Room, till he ſettled his Eſtate upon him, leſt he gave it away; and Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> continued ſo ſecreted, untill Mr. <hi>Henry Wynn,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s Uncle, threatned to move the Houſe of Commons to know where he was; whereupon Mr. <hi>Henry Wynn</hi> was brought to the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> by Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> who was often with him during his reſtraint: during which reſtraint, the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was much threatned by Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi>'s Agents, in the preſence of Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> to ſettle his Eſtate on the ſaid Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his Wife, and their Children; but Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> did then declare, That not any that came of his wife ſhould have one foot of his Eſtate; and at other times declared, That he would be torn in pieces with wilde Horſes, and would give his Eſtate to <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Red-coats, before he would ſettle his Eſtate on his Iſſue Female; and that if he had no Iſſue Male by another wife, he would ſettle his Eſtate on ſome of his Kindred; And during his reſtraint, he deſired Mr. <hi>Henry Wynn</hi> to ſend his Coſin <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> unto him, and did often ſend for the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> during his reſtraint; but <hi>Morris</hi> and <hi>Lewes,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s Servants, denyed to tell him where he was, although the ſaid Mr. <hi>Wynn</hi> promiſed forthwith to procure his Inlargement. After Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was inlarged, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to ſee or receive any Letters from Mr. <hi>Roberts;</hi> and being in his Chamber at the <hi>Temple,</hi> cauſed himſelf to be denied to be within, when Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> ſent or came to him, and turned away his Servants <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Morris</hi> who had betrayed him, who were afterwards retained as Servants by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Roberts.</hi> Afterwards in <hi>May</hi> 1662. <hi>Bodvile</hi> was again arreſted by his Creditors, ſet on by <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Morris;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> ſent for the ſaid Mr. <hi>Tho. Wynn,</hi> who procured him Bayle to ſome of his Actions, and his Liberty, and furniſhed him with the Summe of 220 <hi>l.</hi> and the ſaid Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s wife having procured an Order of Chancery, dated the 12th. of <hi>June</hi> 1662 for his Commitment to the <hi>Fleet.</hi> Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> to avoid ſuch commitment and arreſts, did leave his Chambers at the <hi>Temple,</hi> and gave them unto <hi>Griffith Wynn,</hi> alias <hi>Bodvile,</hi> Sonne of the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn,</hi> who was admitted thereunto, and removed to <hi>Iſlington,</hi> and went by another Name, and cauſed his Servant <hi>Pugh</hi> to change his Name; of which removal or change of his Name Mr. <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> knew nothing, untill he was ſent for by Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> and acquainted therewith by Mr. <hi>Bodvile.</hi> And afterwards Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> in <hi>June</hi> 1662 levied Fines of his Eſtate to enable him to diſpoſe thereof, and imployed his Servant <hi>Pugh</hi> to go into <hi>Wales</hi> for that purpoſe, who was impriſoned by the Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Mrs. <hi>Bodvile.</hi> And in <hi>September</hi> following Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> went from <hi>Iſlington</hi> to the County of <hi>Salop,</hi> and from thence writ ſeveral kinde Letters to Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> and at <hi>Salop</hi> owned him for his great Friend, and the onely Perſon that ſtuck to him in all his troubles: and in <hi>October</hi> following Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> returned to <hi>London,</hi> and went to his Lodgings at <hi>Iſlington;</hi> and in <hi>December</hi> following Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> by reaſon of a Fall, had an Impoſtumation in his Hipp, which put him to great pains, and brought him to be very weak, being for the cure thereof inforced to be launched three Inches at a time, did without the direction, perſwaſion or privity of Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> ſend for Mr. <hi>Pollard,</hi> who was, and antiently had been of his counſell, and much imployed by him, to give him di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for the drawing and preparing his Will; which accordingly being drawn, Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> did peruſe it, and with his own hand did correct a <hi>Welſh</hi> word of the name of a Town therein miſ-written by Mr. <hi>Pollard,</hi> and gave the ſaid Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> direction to call the ſaid <hi>Pugh</hi> into the Chamber, and in their preſence ſigned, ſealed and publiſhed the ſaid Will the 20th. of <hi>December</hi> 1662. and did direct the ſaid Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> and <hi>Pugh</hi> ſhould be witneſſes to the ſaid Will, and wiſhed them to write their Names low, for that he intended to have more witneſſes to the ſaid VVill; and he ſaid <hi>Pugh</hi> deſiring to know the date thereof, Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> ſhewed him the VVill, and Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> wiſhed him to write down the date thereof for his better remembrance; and thereupon Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> locked up the ſaid VVill in a Box, and kept it in his cuſtody. By which VVill Mr. <hi>Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile</hi> gives all his Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments in the Counties of <hi>Carnarvan</hi> and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:180145:4"/>
               <hi>Angleſey</hi> unto Sir <hi>Richard Wynn</hi> and Sir <hi>Tho. Dorrell,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn,</hi> and their Heirs upon ſpecial Truſt and confidence, and to the intent and purpoſe, that they and their Heirs ſhall out of the Rents, Iſſues and Profits thereof, as ſpeedily as they can be collected and raiſed, pay and diſcharge all his juſt and due Debts which he did then owe, or after ſhould contract; and upon further Truſt, that they ſhould raiſe 5000 <hi>l.</hi> for a Portion for his Daughter <hi>Sarah Roberts,</hi> now wife of <hi>Robert Roberts</hi> Eſquire, provided, before payment be made of the ſaid 5000 <hi>l.</hi> that a competent and convenient Proviſion, &amp; Livelyhood be ſettled upon my ſaid Daughter and her Children; and provided alſo, that if the ſaid Mr. <hi>Roberts,</hi> or my ſaid Daughter, or any other Perſon or Perſons claiming by, from, or under them, or either of them diſturb or interrupt my ſaid Truſtees, or any of them, in the quiet reception of the Rents, Iſſues and Profits, according to the Truſt and intent above limited, then the payment of the 5000 <hi>l.</hi> to ceaſe, and no benefit at all to be reaped or received thereby; and after the Debts and Portion ſo ſatisfied and paid her, gave the reſt and reſidue of his ſaid Lands to <hi>Griffith Wynn,</hi> alias <hi>Bodvile,</hi> Son and Heir ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent of the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> and to <hi>Tho. Bodvile</hi> Son of <hi>Alexander Bodvile</hi> late of <hi>Pullhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Carnarvan</hi> Gentleman, deceaſed, and their Heirs reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, equally to be divided between them, without making any diviſion at all of my Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Demeſnes or Tenements thereto belonging; and after ſome other Legacies given by his ſaid VVill, he made the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn</hi> ſole Executor of his ſaid VVill, in truſt only for the more ſpeedy payment and ſatisfying of the ſaid Debts and Portion. In <hi>January</hi> 1662 Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> deſired Mr. <hi>Wynn</hi> to find him out a Lodging in <hi>Black-fryers,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly he did, at the Houſe of one <hi>Clithero,</hi> a mere Stranger to Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> liked well, and went thither the 22 d. day of the ſaid Month; and after he came thither, he went daily abroad. And about a Fortnight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he died, he diſcourſed with Mr. <hi>Edmund Toll</hi> a Proctor, whether they did not in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts proceed in Cauſes of Divorſe; who told him, He believed they did; Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> then told him, His Wife had abuſed him, and deſired him to adviſe with ſome Civilians whether he might not be divorſed from her; and after Mr. <hi>Toll</hi> had adviſed with a Civilian, he told him, they did proceed in cauſes of Divorſe: whereupon Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> ſaid, If it pleaſed God to give him health, he would proceed againſt her; and Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> did then ſhew great diſlike againſt Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his Wife, and ſaid Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> great deſign was to have him ſettle his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate upon him and his Wife, but ſaid his reſolution was never to ſettle his Eſtate upon him, and ſhewed great diſlike againſt him, and told him, That he had levied Fines of his Eſtate in <hi>Wales,</hi> with reſolution to ſettle his Eſtate by Deed or VVill; and that he had made his Will, and that Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> was a Witneſs to it, to whom he had given a Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and thereupon asked, if Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> would ſtand a good VVitneſs? Mr. <hi>Toll</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That if the ſaid Legacy was not ſuch as the Law would conceive might ſway him in his Judgement, his Teſtimony might be good. Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> replyed, to prevent all doubts, If it pleaſed God to recover him to his health, he would deſire him, and 3 or 4 Notary Publiques of <hi>Doctors Commons</hi> to give him a meetting, in whoſe preſence he would then publiſh and declare his Will; and Mr. <hi>Toll</hi> ſayth he was then of a perfect minde and underſtanding to make his VVill. After Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi> the 19th. of <hi>March</hi> 1662 in the preſence of Mr. <hi>Wandesford,</hi> Mr. <hi>Griffith,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Platt,</hi> three more VVitneſſes, without exception he did declare unto them, That he had ſent for them to be VVitneſſes to his VVill, which he had formerly made and publiſhed, but that he did lodge in an obſcure place where he made his ſaid VVill, and went by another Name; and having the ſaid VVill in his hands, he read over part thereof in their preſence, both at the beginning and latter end thereof, and ſhewed them the Seal he formerly ſealed his Will with, and deſired them to compare the ſaid Seal and the former impreſſion together; which they did, and found them agree, and then in their preſence did publiſh and declare his Will again, and diſcourſed very rationally with them both concerning his Will and other matters; by which Will he hath given his ſaid Daughter as much as upon the Marriage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement was thought fit all his Daughters ſhould have, if never ſo many, if he died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Iſſue Male. After which he deſired a Miniſter might be ſent for; which was done, with whom he diſcourſed very rationally, and fully and diſcreetly anſwered to all ſuch things as are uſually put to ſick Perſons; and the ſaid Miniſter adviſing him to make a Will and ſettle his Eſtate for the quieting of his Conſcience, and to be at peace with all the World. He ſaid, he had done that already. Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> died 28 <hi>March</hi> 1663. after which Mr. <hi>Bodviles</hi> wife and Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> enter upon the whole Eſtate of Mr. <hi>Bodvile,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:180145:5"/>and ever ſince and yet do continue the poſſeſſion. And 27 <hi>April</hi> 1663. Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his wife, and <hi>Charles Bodvile Roberts</hi> their ſecond Son, exhibit a Bill in <hi>Chancery</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Tho. Wynn,</hi> the Truſtees, <hi>Griffith Wynn</hi> alias <hi>Bodvile, Tho. Bodvile, Timothy Pollard,</hi> and others, to ſet aſide the ſaid Will, ſuggeſting that the ſaid Will was procured by fraud and practice from Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> when he was in a weak condition both of body and minde, when he was ſecreted from all his Friends, and that he was not <hi>compos mentis</hi> when he made the ſaid Will, and that Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> had a great diſaffection to the ſaid <hi>Tho. Wynn.</hi> In <hi>May</hi> following there was an Injunction granted, which was continued to the Hearing of the Cauſe; which was heard the 19th. of <hi>January;</hi> upon which Hearing the Lord Chancellor being aſſiſted with the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Hyde,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Bridgman</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they could not relieve the Plaintiffs, but left the Plaintiffs to ſeek relief as they ſhould be adviſed, but yet continued the Injunction; after Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his wife ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed themſelves to the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in Parliament aſſembled, who after very many Hearings and Debates 29 <hi>November</hi> 1664 referred it back to the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor to make a Decree according to equity and juſtice on either ſide, though there was no Preſident in the Caſe. After the 12th. of <hi>July</hi> 1666 the Lord Chancellor being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with the Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Bridgman,</hi> the Lord Chief Baron <hi>Hales,</hi> and Baron <hi>Rainsford</hi> reheard the ſaid Cauſe, and ſpent 3 dayes therein; wherein nothing was omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that could be ſaid or obſerved for the Plaintiffs advantage. But their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips were all fully of opinion, That the Plaintiffs were not releiveable, and did order that the matter of the Plaintiffs Bill be from thenceforth clearly and alſo fully diſmiſt out of the ſaid Court without coſts; and that all Injunctions in the ſaid Cauſe be from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth abſolutely diſsolved: As for the ſuggeſtions made by Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his Councill that this Will was gained by the fraud and practice of <hi>Tho. Wynn:</hi> It did not appear by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny proof that Mr. <hi>Tho. VVynn</hi> did ever move or ſpeak to Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> to make any Will or ſettlement of his Eſtate, nor did know that he had given any Inſtructions for the making of his VVill at <hi>Iſlington,</hi> or that he had made any Will at <hi>Iſlington;</hi> and as for Mr. <hi>Bodviles</hi> ſecreting himſelf from his friends and going to <hi>Iſlington,</hi> He had great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to ſecret himſelf to free himſelf from arreſts, and other proſecutions of his Wife, but it could not be proved neither is there any truth in it, that the ſame was done by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, councill, adviſe, or privity of the ſaid <hi>Tho. VVynn,</hi> or that the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVynn</hi> knew where he was till long after his removall that he ſent for him; and it is clear in proof that Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> and his Wife was 3 times with Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> the very week he died; and when directions were given by the Phyſitian that they ſhould not let company come to him, it being asked by the Woman of the Houſe of Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> What if Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> or his Wife come, may not they be let in, Mr. <hi>Wynn</hi> anſwered, Let them come to him by all means. As for his being <hi>non compos mentis,</hi> and under an habitual madneſs, if that were true it is properly tryable at Law; but the evidence is ſo plain by 10 Witneſſes at the leaſt of good credit, as alſo by his Letters and accounts of the daily expences of his own writing, that he was of a diſpoſing memory and underſtanding, that all Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that nature are ſilenced; and as for his diſaffection to Mr. <hi>Wynn,</hi> and the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full language he gave him, It is fully in proof, that he bore a greater diſaffection to Mr. <hi>Roberts;</hi> but it doth appear both by his words, actions, and ſeveral Letters under his own hand, written about ſix Months before his death, that he had a great kindneſs or reſpect for the ſaid Mr. <hi>VVynn,</hi> and that he valued and eſteemed him more than any other Kinſman, put him in ſeveral Deeds of Truſt; and upon the death of his Daughter <hi>Eliz.</hi> he ſent Mr. <hi>VVynn</hi> and his Wife and Children Mourning. Ever ſince the death of Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi> the Truſtees have been and yet are kept out of the Eſtate, not one penny of Mr. <hi>Bodvile</hi>'s Debts, which are great, are yet paid out of the Eſtate, but the Eſtate injoyed by Mr. <hi>Roberts;</hi> and although the Injunctions be now diſſolved, yet the Truſtees cannot ſue at Law, by reaſon of Mr. <hi>Roberts</hi> Priviledge of Parliament. All which is humbly ſubmitted to the Judgement and Conſideration of the Honourable Houſe of Commons.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
